# Vikram Kamath Cannanure

POSTDOCTORAL FELLOW - SAARLAND UNIVERSITY · HCI, ICTD, AI, EDUCATION

vica001@teams.uni-saarland.de ⋅ ★ kmarkiv.com ⋅ □ kmarkiv

kmarkiv.com ⋅ □ kmarkiv

I am a postdoctoral fellow at Saarland University, researching the role of AI in supporting marginalized audiences in the Global South. I completed my PhD at Carnegie Mellon University, specializing in Human-Computer Interaction (HCI) and Information Technology and Development (ICTD). My thesis focused on developing a chatbot to support professional development for primary teachers in rural Côte d'Ivoire. My system was used by over 400 teachers and impacted over 10,000 students. I have worked on projects in Côte d'Ivoire, Rwanda, the US, Macau, Germany and India. My work has been published in top-tier HCI conferences. In addition to research, I co-led "HCI Across Borders," workshop for junior researchers from different geographies for over 5 years, mentored over 20 students and reviewed over 40 papers in HCI.

### **Education**

#### **Carnegie Mellon University**

Pittsburgh, USA

PhD, Human-Computer Interaction

2017- Aug 2023

- · Advisors: Prof. Tim Brown and Prof. Amy Ogan
- Committee: Prof. Chinmay Kulkarni, Prof. Mayank Goel, and Prof. Kentaro Toyama (University of Michigan)
- Thesis: DIA: Supporting Teacher Professional Development in Low Infrastructure Settings
- Research involved field work and technology deployment in rural Côte d'Ivoire

#### **Carnegie Mellon University**

Pittsburgh, USA

MASTERS, HUMAN-COMPUTER INTERACTION

2017-2021

#### **Carnegie Mellon University**

Pittsburgh, USA

MASTERS, EDUCATIONAL TECHNOLOGY AND APPLIED LEARNING SCIENCE

2014-2015

#### **National Institute of Technology Karnataka**

Karnataka, India

BACHELOR OF TECHNOLOGY, MECHANICAL ENGINEERING

2007-2011

# **Research Experience**

Saarland University Saarbrücken, Germany

POSTDOCTORAL FELLOW

October 2023 – present

- Advisor: Prof. Ingmar Weber
- Supervising PhD students on projects related to HCI4D and NLP
- Exploring the role of Generative AI for various projects in the Global South

#### Carnegie Mellon University, Africa

Kigali, Rwanda

Summer 2018, Summer 2019, Fall 2020

· Host: Prof. Tim Brown

VISITING RESEARCHER

- Project: Design of a Phone Call-Based Health Information System
- · Conducted participatory research with rural women and prototyped an IVR system in rural Rwanda

#### **United Nations University Computing and Society**

Macau, SAR, China

RESEARCH INTERN

July 2017 - Sept 2017

- Advisor: Dr. Mamello Thinayne
- Conducted participatory design with a local NGO
- Built a mobile app to report and monitor homelessness in Macau

#### **Carnegie Mellon University**

Pittsburgh, USA

Aug. 2015 - June. 2017

- RESEARCH ASSISTANT
- Advisor: Prof. Jen Mankoff
- Longitudinal eating detection: deployed and evaluated the system to 12 users in the field
- Twist n Knock: A one-handed Gesture for smart watches: publication at GI 2016 [C1]
- EDigs: Built and maintained the APIs for apartment hunting website in Pittsburgh [C3]

JUNE 12, 2024 VIKRAM KAMATH · KMARKIV.COM

## **Awards**

2023	SIGCHI Development grant, HCIxB Workshop at CHI - 8000 USD	
2019	PhD Fellowship, Center for Machine Learning and Health - 100,000 USD	Pittsburgh PA
2019	Best Paper Award, ACM COMPASS Paper	Accra, Ghana
2019	Poster Spotlight, ACM COMPASS Poster	Accra, Ghana

## **Selected Publications**

For full list see https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=HVuuUzwAAAAJ

- [11] **Cannanure V.K.**, Ngoon T., Wolf S., Jasinska K., Brown T., Ogan A. *Understanding the Longitudinal Impacts of a Chatbot to Facilitate a Virtual Community of Practice for Teachers in rural Côte d'Ivoire*. ACM COMPASS 2024, Delhi, India.
- [10] Ngoon T., **Cannanure V.K.**, Wolf S., Jasinska K., Brown T., Ogan A. "I believe I did not preach into the desert": Opportunities & Challenges in Scaling Teacher Mentorship through Mobile Technology in Rural Côte d'Ivoire. L@Scale 2024, Atlanta, USA.
- [9] **Cannanure V.K.**, Ávila E., Ngoon T., Adji Y., Wolf S., Jasinska K., Brown T., Ogan A. "We dream of climbing the ladder, for getting there, we have to do our job better": Designing for Teacher Aspirations in rural Côte d'Ivoire. ACM COMPASS 2022, Seattle, USA.
- [8] **Cannanure V.K.**, Brown T., Ogan A. *DIA: A Human AI Hybrid Chatbot for Low Resource Contexts*. ICTD 2020, Guayaquil, Ecuador
- [7] **Cannanure V.K.**, Souvenir J., Adji Y., Apke H., Jasinska K., Brown T., Ogan A. "I'm fine where I am, but I want to do more": Exploring Teacher Aspirations in Rural Cote D'Ivoire. ACM COMPASS 2020, Guayaquil, Ecuador
- [6] Madaio, M., Yarzebinski, E., **Cannanure V.K.**, Zinszer B., Seri, A., Tanoh, F., Hannon-Cropp, J., Cassell, J., Jasinska, K., Ogan, A. *Collective Support and Independent Learning with a Voice-Based Literacy Technology in Rural Communities*. CHI '20, Apr 2020, Hawaii, USA
- [5] Madaio, M., **Cannanure V.K.**, Yarzebinski, E., Zasacky, S., Tanoh, F., Hannon-Cropp, J., Cassell, J., Jasinska, K., Ogan, A. "You Give a Little of Yourself": Family Support for Children's Use of an IVR Literacy System. COMPASS '19, Jun 2019, Accra, Ghana
- [4] **Cannanure V.K.**, Brown T, *RASP-IVR: A Low Cost Interactive Voice Response System*. AfriCHI '18, December 2018, Windhoek, Namibia.
- [3] Onafuwa, D., Early, K., Vyas N, **Cannanure V.K.**, Mankoff J. *Understanding the Information Needs of Prospective Tenants*. ACM SIGCAS Conference on Computing and Sustainable Societies (COMPASS 2018), June 2018, San Francisco, USA.
- [2] Bhat, K.\*, Thinayane M.\*, Goldkind L., **Cannanure V.K.** *Critical Participatory Design: Reflections on engagement and empowerment in a case of a Community Based Organization*. Participatory Design Conference (PDC 2018), August 2018, Hasselt and Genk, Belgium.
- [1] **Cannanure V.K.**, Chen, X., Mankoff J., *Twist and Knock A One-Handed Gesture for Smart Watches*. Proceedings of the 42nd Graphics Interface Conference (GI 2016)

# **Teaching Experience**

#### Programming Usable Interfaces (05-430/05630)

TEACHING ASSISTANT. INSTRUCTOR: SCOTT HUDSON
Carnegie Mellon University

Spring 2022

#### User-Centered Research & Evaluation (05-410/05-610)

TEACHING ASSISTANT. INSTRUCTOR: RAELIN MUSURACA Carnegie Mellon University Spring 2021

## **Professional Service**

2024	<b>Lead Organizer</b> , HCI Across Borders (HCIxB) workshop at ACM COMPASS	Delhi, India
2023	Lead Organizer, HCI Across Borders (HCIxB) workshop at CHI	Hamburg, Germany
2022	Lead Organizer, HCI Across Borders (HCIxB) workshop at CHI	New Orleans, USA
2021	Lead Organizer, HCI Across Borders (HCIxB) workshop at CHI	Yokohama, Japan
2020	Organizer, HCI Across Borders (HCIxB) symposium at CHI	Hawaii, USA
2019	Organizer, HCI Across Borders (HCIxB) symposium at CHI	Glasgow, UK
2019	Organizer, Young Researchers reception ICTDx	Ahmedabad
2020-22	SIGCHI Development Fund, Executive Committee	
2020-	AC, CHI 22 (extended abstract), CHI 21 (extended abstract), CHI 20 (extended abstract)	
2018-	<b>Reviewer</b> , ACM COMPASS 2021, CSCW 2021, CHI 2021, CHI 21 (case studies), CSCW 20, CHI 20 (case	
	studies), CHI 19, HCIxB 2019, DIS 18 (WiP), PDC 18(Notes)	

# **Mentoring**

PhD

**Ethel Mensa**: Saarland University, PhD: Exploring structural inequality in Germany using POI data **Hamayoon Behmanush**: Saarland University, PhD: Supporting Afghan women learn programming

#### Masters

Divya Mani Adhikari: Saarland University, MS 2024: Automated Survey Testing using LLMs Prithika Acharya: CMU Pittsburgh, METALS 2022: Teacher Training Project in Ivory Coast Aastha Patel: CMU Pittsburgh, METALS 2022: Teacher Training Project in Ivory Coast Egide Kamuzinzi: CMU Rwanda, MSIT 2021: Teacher Training Project in Ivory Coast Baptiste Moreau-Pernet: CMU Pittsburgh, METALS 2021: Teacher Training Project in Ivory Coast **Saumya Sharma**: CMU Pittsburgh, MSIIPM 2020: Simple Health Information System Lucie Uwimpaye: CMU Africa, MSIT 2021: Simple Health Information System **Eloísa Ávila**: CMU Pittsburgh, MSPPM 2021: Teacher Training Project in Ivory Coast **Sheila Mbadi**: CMU Africa, MSIT 2021: Simple Health Information System Patrick Manirakiza: CMU Africa, MSECE 2019: MnE system for Rwanda Women's Network **Solange lyubu**:CMU Africa, MSECE 2019: MnE system for Rwanda Women's Network Sabin Sheja: CMU Africa, MSECE 2019: MnE system for Rwanda Women's Network Justin Bigwi: CMU Africa, MSECE 2019: Design of a Phone Call-Based Health Information System Gloria Umutesi: CMU Africa, MSECE 2020: Design of a Phone Call-Based Health Information System Jocelyne Mukamisha CMU Africa, MSIT 2020: Design of a Phone Call-Based Health Information System Justin Souvenir Niweteto: CMU Africa, MSIT 2020: Design of a Phone Call-Based Health Information System Fraterne Kagame CMU Africa, MSIT 2020: Design of a Phone Call-Based Health Information System Huguette Ingenere: CMU Africa, MSIT 2020: French Interview Transcription for teachers in Cote d'Ivoire Marie Claudine Ingenere: CMU Africa, MSIT 2020: French Interview Transcription for teachers in Cote d'Ivoire Nebiyou Yismaw: CMU Africa, MSECE 2018: Digital and Voice based Systems to support GBV Fabiola Uwashema: CMU Africa, MSIT 2018: Digital and Voice based Systems to support GBV

#### Undergraduate

**Riti Verma**: Indian Institute of Technology, Delhi: *Exploring the role of AI in the Global South* **Lena Armstrong**: University of Pennsylvania, Summer REU: *Teacher Training Project in Ivory Coast* **Maya Greenholt**: CMU Pittsburgh, Cognitive Science: *Teacher Training Project in Ivory Coast* 

# Skills\_

Programming	Python, PHP, HTML/CSS, JavaScript, Android, Arduino, iOS
Technologies	Pandas, Scikit, Weka, NumPy, AngularJS, Three.js, Bootstrap, MySQL, MongoDB, Redis, WebSockets
Coursework	Applied Fabrication, Applied Machine Learning, Data Pipeline, Gadgets Activity and Recognition in HCI, Education Goals,
Coursework	E-Learning Design Principles, Game Design Studio, Design of Educational Games

## Selected Press\_\_\_\_\_

**The Next Web** TeliportMe introduces 3D effects to its 360-degree panoramic app for Android **Techcrunch** Test Flighting: Applover Launches Free, Crowdsourced Testing Platform for Android Apps **Robert Scoble** Developers: crowd-source your testing of Android phones **CMLA** Prove a line recovered from Correction Mellon University cools to be less poor less find the parfect rent

**CMU** A new online resource from Carnegie Mellon University seeks to help people find the perfect rental **HCII** EDigs Helps Apartment Hunters Find the Perfect Rental

**TheBetterIndia** How a National Level Cyclist Is Fighting Both Spinal Injury & Poverty with Inspiring Confidence **Milaap Blog** Getting Back to Cycling: A National Medalist's Dream

# **Professional Experience**

#### **Carnegie Mellon University**

Pittsburgh, USA

SENIOR WEB DEVELOPER

July 2015 - June 2017

- · Advisor: Prof. Geoff Gordon
- Built and managed educational technology to support online learning
- Prototyping low cost video recording system for teaching courses

#### TeliportMe Inc: Indian startup

Karnataka, IN Jul 2011- Aug 2014

WEB ARCHITECT

- Engineered APIs for Android, iOS, Web and Google Glass
- Scaled back-end to handle 4 million users and mange 100K locations
- Designed 3D viewer on par with Google street view
- Managed 10 Ubuntu machines with MySQL and Redis replication

## Other\_\_\_

- Philanthropy I have raised over \$20,000 for charity for various causes in India
- Android I have deployed 3 apps to the app store and have around 10,000 active users
- **Web** I have deployed over 20 websites to production. My best project has reached over 4 million users.
- Teaching I teach children a second language(Kannada) at the S.V. Temple in Pittsburgh
- Swimming I swam 10 miles from Elephanta Caves to Gateway of India to raise money for acid attack victims